<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>variables on StatPREP Workshops 2019</title>
    <link>/tags/variables/</link>
    <description>Recent content in variables on StatPREP Workshops 2019</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 04 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/variables/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Instructor Guide: Data basics</title>
      <link>/blog/instructions-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/instructions-data/</guid>
      <description>Activities  Variable types Variables and units Response and explanatory variables   Learning objectives  Additional resources  Get formatted versions: Word : PDF Instructor orientation Role in statistical practice Classroom discussion Assessment Tips for an active classroom Student pre-requisites Pitfalls   Orientation for instructors Explaining what is data and what are the forms of data.
Role in statistical practice  Conceptual pitfalls  Student pre-requisites  Student tasks and activities  Creating an active classroom See the document on general tips for creating an active classroom.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Variables and the unit of observation</title>
      <link>/blog/activity-variables-and-units/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/activity-variables-and-units/</guid>
      <description>Get formatted versions: Word : PDF
Orientation There’s an expression about how to accomplish a complex, confusing, and difficult task: One step at a time. The purpose of this lesson is to provide you with a step-by-step procedure for working with data. Each step can be straightforward. Some steps involve informing yourself about the data at hand. Some steps require creativity and insight about the real-world system the data represents.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Response and explanatory variables</title>
      <link>/blog/activity-response-and-explanatory/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/activity-response-and-explanatory/</guid>
      <description>Get formatted versions: Word : PDF
Orientation A variable is a quantity or characteristic that varies from one person to another, or more generally, from one unit of observation to another. There are two distinct types of variables: quantitative (numeric) and categorical (labels/words/etc.).
There’s another distinction to be made about variables, which is not about the type of the variable itself but the role the variable will play in the statistical methods we use to describe a situation of interest and the relationships among the variables involved.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data and Point Plots</title>
      <link>/blog/activity-point-plot/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/activity-point-plot/</guid>
      <description>Get formatted versions: Word : PDF
Orientation Data can be many things, but one of the most common formats is a data frame, a kind of spreadsheet of rows and columns. We’ll work with the data frame Births_2014, which is based on data published by the US Centers for Disease Control. Births_2014 has 100,000 rows. Each row reports a live birth in the US in 2014. There are dozens of variables, a few of which are shown below.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>You Want to Know: Cases, Variables, and Study Goals</title>
      <link>/blog/activity-you-want-to-know/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/activity-you-want-to-know/</guid>
      <description>Instructions. In each scenario below,
 determine what variables you would need to collect and whether each is categorical or quantitative,
 describe or sketch a graph you would make to give you an initial impression regarding the answer to the question of interest,
 determine the parameter(s) of interest and explain how they are different from the variables,
   determine whether you are using a paired design.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>You Want to Know: What&#39;s the Point</title>
      <link>/blog/instructions-you-want-to-know/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/instructions-you-want-to-know/</guid>
      <description>The You Want to Know activity is just one example among many similar activities. This instructors’ activity explores ways you can construct many similar activities for your students.
How to make your own activity The key steps to creating these activities are
Determine the learning objectives. These might include
Making key distinctions like case/variable, categorical/quantitative, explantory/reponse, etc. Identifying key elements of study design. Selecting appropriate analysis methods. Use of software to acheive a task (have students write R command or describe how to use other software)  Design the questions.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>