<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Activity Guide on StatPREP Workshops 2019</title>
    <link>/categories/activity-guide/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Activity Guide on StatPREP Workshops 2019</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/activity-guide/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Instructor Guide: Data basics</title>
      <link>/blog/instructions-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/instructions-data/</guid>
      <description>Activities  Variable types Variables and units Response and explanatory variables   Learning objectives  Additional resources  Get formatted versions: Word : PDF Instructor orientation Role in statistical practice Classroom discussion Assessment Tips for an active classroom Student pre-requisites Pitfalls   Orientation for instructors Explaining what is data and what are the forms of data.
Role in statistical practice  Conceptual pitfalls  Student pre-requisites  Student tasks and activities  Creating an active classroom See the document on general tips for creating an active classroom.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Instructor Guide: Graphing Data</title>
      <link>/blog/instructions-graphing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/instructions-graphing/</guid>
      <description>Activities  Point plots Jittering and violins Summary intervals Response and explanatory variables   Learning objectives  Additional resources  Get formatted versions: Word : PDF Instructor orientation Role in statistical practice Classroom discussion Assessment Tips for an active classroom Student pre-requisites Pitfalls   Orientation for instructors Showing the basic kinds of plots: data/density/interval
Role in statistical practice  Conceptual pitfalls  Learning objectives  Student background  Background data knowledge  (If we had) the population  Student tasks and activities  Creating an active classroom See the document on general tips for creating an active classroom.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating an Active Classroom</title>
      <link>/blog/instructions-active-classroom-tips/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/instructions-active-classroom-tips/</guid>
      <description>Tips for Creating an Active Classroom Make your lectures active, too.
It is tempting to equate “active learning” with “group work”, Think about ways to make lectures more active for students. Interject questions (and wait for answers). Mix in short “your turn” exercises or “think-pair-share” questions. Use “call and response”. Ask students to guess computer commands before introducing new commands.
Ask lots of questions.
 But don’t answer them yourself.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Instructor Guide: Causality</title>
      <link>/blog/instructions-causality/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/instructions-causality/</guid>
      <description>Activities  Intervention and prediction Experiment and causality   Learning objectives  Additional sections  Get formatted versions: Word : PDF Instructor orientation Role in statistical practice Classroom discussion Tips for an active classroom Student pre-requisites Pitfalls   Orientation for instructors There is an epigram that is familiar to all statistics instructors:
 Correlation is not causation.
 Put on a more explicit logical footing, this is equivalent to:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Instructor guide: Center &amp; spread</title>
      <link>/blog/instructions-center-spread/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/instructions-center-spread/</guid>
      <description>Activities  Variables and their summary intervals The standard deviation and the summary interval Shapes of distributions The normal distribution   Learning objectives Summarize the likely range of a variable using an interval. Choose the summary interval endpoints to include the “vast majority” of the values. Master the convention that “vast majority” is the central 95% of the values. Be able to work with two formats for describing an interval: “A to B” and “C ± D”.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Instructor Guide: Confidence intervals</title>
      <link>/blog/instructions-confidence-intervals/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/instructions-confidence-intervals/</guid>
      <description>Activities  What is a confidence interval? Sampling bias and confidence intervals Comparing two groups Comparing two confidence intervals Two-sample t test   Learning objectives connected to confidence intervals  Master the relevant vocabulary … population, sample, sample statistic, point estimate, margin of error, confidence interval, confidence level. Recognize the estimation process that leads to a confidence interval: a sample is selected randomly from a population a statistic is calculated from that sample the margin of error and, correspondingly, the confidence interval are calculated from that sample.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>You Want to Know: What&#39;s the Point?</title>
      <link>/blog/instructions-you-want-to-know/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/instructions-you-want-to-know/</guid>
      <description>The You Want to Know activity is just one example among many similar activities. This instructors’ activity explores ways you can construct many similar activities for your students.
How to make your own activity The key steps to creating these activities are
Determine the learning objectives. These might include
Making key distinctions like case/variable, categorical/quantitative, explantory/reponse, etc. Identifying key elements of study design. Selecting appropriate analysis methods. Use of software to acheive a task (have students write R command or describe how to use other software)  Design the questions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Instructor Guide: Two-sample t-test</title>
      <link>/blog/instructions-two-sample-t-test/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/instructions-two-sample-t-test/</guid>
      <description>Activities  Comparing two groups Comparing confidence intervals Two sample t-test Instructor customizations:  Ambika Silva: Comparing two samples with confidence intervals activity &amp;amp; assessment    Learning objectives Typical course objectives relating to the t-based test and confidence interval are:
 Confidence interval:  Compute from data the confidence interval on the difference of means. Interpret the confidence interval in the context of the question intended to be addressed with the data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Instructor Guide: Introducing the normal distribution</title>
      <link>/blog/instructions-normal-distribution/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/instructions-normal-distribution/</guid>
      <description>Activities  Distribution shapes Normal parameters Common and rare   Learning objectives  Understand how a distribution summarizes the properties of a collection of individual values. Be able to translate between major forms of representing distributions graphically, e.g.  the density of points in a (jittered) point plot the presentation of such density as a height or width as in a violin or density plot  Be able to eyeball the standard deviation of a close-to-normal distribution and, similarly, a 95% summary interval (that is, mean ± two standard deviations ) Be able to identify common characteristics of skew or long-tailed distributions, by comparison to a normal distribution.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Instructor Guide: Linear Regression</title>
      <link>/blog/instructions-linear-regression/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/instructions-linear-regression/</guid>
      <description>Activities  Introducing linear regression Describing relationship patterns How much is explained by regression?   Learning objectives connected to linear regression  Create scatterplots for bivariate data using graphing technology where appropriate. Lesson: point plots Sensibly choose which variable should be the response and which the explanatory variable, and know when it does and doesn’t matter. (Other nomenclature for explanatory/response: predictor/response or independent/dependent.) Lesson: response and explanatory variables  External evidence of which direction causation goes, e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tips for an active classroom</title>
      <link>/blog/tips-for-active-classroom/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/tips-for-active-classroom/</guid>
      <description>Many instructors believe that learning is enhanced in a classroom where students are active participants rather than the passive recipients of a lecture. This document describes some general techniques for fostering an active classroom that can be used in a wide range of lesson topics. (There are also tips for specific topics included in the instructor guide for each topic.)
What’s key is to constantly look for opportunities to force students to make a choice, offer a suggestion, or state an interpretation or an opinion.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>