<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>computing on StatPREP Workshops 2019</title>
    <link>/categories/computing/</link>
    <description>Recent content in computing on StatPREP Workshops 2019</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 29 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/computing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to RStudio.cloud</title>
      <link>/blog/technology/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/technology/</guid>
      <description>Background Setup your account on RStudio Cloud Running Little Apps   Background The GAISE report’s Recommendation 5 is
 Use technology to explore concepts and analyze data.
 Elaborations on this recommendation are contained in Appendix D of the report, and include
 interactive applets, pp. 66-75 I think of these as a mouse-driven form of computation that requires absolutely no “coding” statistical software. GAISE speaks of “a package like SPSS, Minitab, JMP, R, StatCrunch, Stata, any of the many Excel add-ins, or on-line tools …”  “to teach concepts” “to create a wider variety of visualizations”, pp.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>R Tutorials for instructors</title>
      <link>/blog/tutorials/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/tutorials/</guid>
      <description>StatPREP tutorials A StatPREP tutorial is an interactive document mainly intended to help instructors develop statistical, graphical, and general computing skills using R statements.
This page provides links to instructor tutorials. Each link takes you to a web service that displays the document in your web browser. You don’t need to install any other software on your computer to use the lessons and tutorials.
If you’re looking for materials for use in class or other student-oriented settings, follow these links to StatPREP activites or Little Apps</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>