<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Normal Distribution on StatPREP Workshops 2019</title>
    <link>/tags/normal-distribution/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Normal Distribution on StatPREP Workshops 2019</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/normal-distribution/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Instructor guide: Center &amp; spread</title>
      <link>/blog/instructions-center-spread/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/instructions-center-spread/</guid>
      <description>Activities  Variables and their summary intervals The standard deviation and the summary interval Shapes of distributions The normal distribution   Learning objectives Summarize the likely range of a variable using an interval. Choose the summary interval endpoints to include the “vast majority” of the values. Master the convention that “vast majority” is the central 95% of the values. Be able to work with two formats for describing an interval: “A to B” and “C ± D”.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Instructor Guide: Introducing the normal distribution</title>
      <link>/blog/instructions-normal-distribution/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/instructions-normal-distribution/</guid>
      <description>Activities  Distribution shapes Normal parameters Common and rare   Learning objectives  Understand how a distribution summarizes the properties of a collection of individual values. Be able to translate between major forms of representing distributions graphically, e.g.  the density of points in a (jittered) point plot the presentation of such density as a height or width as in a violin or density plot  Be able to eyeball the standard deviation of a close-to-normal distribution and, similarly, a 95% summary interval (that is, mean ± two standard deviations ) Be able to identify common characteristics of skew or long-tailed distributions, by comparison to a normal distribution.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>