<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>StatPREP Workshops 2019</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on StatPREP Workshops 2019</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 30 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Providing links to your students</title>
      <link>/blog/activity-instructor-instructions/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/activity-instructor-instructions/</guid>
      <description>The documents on this site are formatted for instructors. There are also documents formatted for students. * If you want to hand out a printed version of the activity, there is a link to a Word format near the top of each document. Feel free to customize this to suit your own class! * If you prefer to give your students a URL so they can access the document via the web, we suggest you give them the Student link that can be found in each document.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Little Apps: Orientation</title>
      <link>/blog/la-orientation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/la-orientation/</guid>
      <description>Little Apps provide interactive computing with no coding to calculate statistics, fit models, and display statistical concepts.
Every Little App is built around a common framework:
 At the core is a data graphic. The vertical axis is the response variable and the horizontal axis is the explanatory variable. Controls enable you to select a data set and variables. Set the sample size and easily display a new sample. Statistics are shown as annotations, always with respect to the data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Instructor Guide: Data basics</title>
      <link>/blog/instructions-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/instructions-data/</guid>
      <description>Activities  Variable types Variables and units Response and explanatory variables   Learning objectives  Additional resources  Get formatted versions: Word : PDF Instructor orientation Role in statistical practice Classroom discussion Assessment Tips for an active classroom Student pre-requisites Pitfalls   Orientation for instructors Explaining what is data and what are the forms of data.
Role in statistical practice  Conceptual pitfalls  Student pre-requisites  Student tasks and activities  Creating an active classroom See the document on general tips for creating an active classroom.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Jittering</title>
      <link>/blog/activity-jittering/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/activity-jittering/</guid>
      <description>Get formatted versions: Word : PDF
Orientation Graphical displays are effective when they connect well with human visual and cognitive faculties. Humans are extremely good at some visual tasks and surprisingly poor at others. To illustrate, consider the task of identifying how many 3’s there are in the following list:
The task is difficult because recognizing shapes is a tough cognitive task.
The task becomes much simpler if we take advantage of color, which our visual systems can process very quickly.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Instructor Guide: Graphing Data</title>
      <link>/blog/instructions-graphing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/instructions-graphing/</guid>
      <description>Activities  Point plots Jittering and violins Summary intervals Response and explanatory variables   Learning objectives  Additional resources  Get formatted versions: Word : PDF Instructor orientation Role in statistical practice Classroom discussion Assessment Tips for an active classroom Student pre-requisites Pitfalls   Orientation for instructors Showing the basic kinds of plots: data/density/interval
Role in statistical practice  Conceptual pitfalls  Learning objectives  Student background  Background data knowledge  (If we had) the population  Student tasks and activities  Creating an active classroom See the document on general tips for creating an active classroom.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome</title>
      <link>/blog/presentation-welcome/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/presentation-welcome/</guid>
      <description>What are you looking for?  What challenges do you face?  What are institutional challenges  Background and experience From the pre-workshop survey
 Institution type  Two-year college 17/34 Four year institution 16/34  Grad-school discipline  Mathematics 30 / 34 Statistics 9 / 34 OR / Economics / Healthcare Admin 3 / 34  Statistics experience  studied applied statistics in grad school 18 / 31 studied theoretical statistics in grad school 15 / 33 do applied statistics outside of teaching 10 / 34  Teaching experience: number with &amp;gt; 2 years experience  “other” mathematics 26 / 31  intro stat 23 / 32 (2 have no experience) college algebra 21 / 31  calculus (1 has no experience) 19 / 31 non-intro statistics (7 have no experience) 13 / 31   Changing faster and faster … How has the content and application of our field changed?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to RStudio.cloud</title>
      <link>/blog/technology/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/technology/</guid>
      <description>Background Setup your account on RStudio Cloud Running Little Apps   IN DRAFT: Make a link to the RStudio webinar on Wednesday about cloud.
Background The GAISE report’s Recommendation 5 is
 Use technology to explore concepts and analyze data.
 Elaborations on this recommendation are contained in Appendix D of the report, and include
 interactive applets, pp. 66-75 I think of these as a mouse-driven form of computation that requires absolutely no “coding” statistical software.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to data graphics</title>
      <link>/blog/la-point-plot/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/la-point-plot/</guid>
      <description>Point plot Little App: Baby weight versus gestation in Births_2014. Click here to launch.   
The point-plot Little App provides a quick path to making data graphics. Select the data set, the response and explanatory variables, and you’re there.
 You can map color to a covariate and can facet the graph (as shown above) by another covariate. Works with both quantitative and categorical variables on either or both axes, for color, and for faceting.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Types of variables</title>
      <link>/blog/activity-variable-types/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/activity-variable-types/</guid>
      <description>Get formatted versions: Word : PDF
Orientation There are two major types of variables:
 Quantitative, where the value of the variable is a number. Categorical, where the value of the variable is one of a set of labels. That is, the value tells which category or group the row falls into.  Quantitative variables cover an interval of the number line. That interval is described by two numbers: the minimum value and the maximum value of the variable.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Jittering</title>
      <link>/blog/la-jittering/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/la-jittering/</guid>
      <description>  Jittering Little App: Self-described level of health versus frequency of feeling depressed in the National Health and Nutrition Evaluation Survey. Click here to launch.   
The Jittering Little App shows how the general point-plot can be effective even when variables are categorical.
 Students can adjust the amount of jittering and transparency. Can stratify sampling by the explanatory variable.  Suggested StatPREP 101 activities  Jittering activity   </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Proportions</title>
      <link>/blog/la-proportions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/la-proportions/</guid>
      <description>Proportions Little App: Among births in the US, does the probability of an induced delivery vary with the length of gestation? Click here to launch.   
The Proportions Little App allows you to explore how the probability of a categorical outcome varies with either categorical or quantitative variables.
 Choose the level of the response variable for which you want to know the proportion. Display confidence intervals/bands.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Variables and the unit of observation</title>
      <link>/blog/activity-variables-and-units/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/activity-variables-and-units/</guid>
      <description>Get formatted versions: Word : PDF
Orientation There’s an expression about how to accomplish a complex, confusing, and difficult task: One step at a time. The purpose of this lesson is to provide you with a step-by-step procedure for working with data. Each step can be straightforward. Some steps involve informing yourself about the data at hand. Some steps require creativity and insight about the real-world system the data represents. Some steps require application of a particular technical procedure.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Response and explanatory variables</title>
      <link>/blog/activity-response-and-explanatory/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/activity-response-and-explanatory/</guid>
      <description>Get formatted versions: Word : PDF
Orientation A variable is a quantity or characteristic that varies from one person to another, or more generally, from one unit of observation to another. There are two distinct types of variables: quantitative (numeric) and categorical (labels/words/etc.).
There’s another distinction to be made about variables, which is not about the type of the variable itself but the role the variable will play in the statistical methods we use to describe a situation of interest and the relationships among the variables involved.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Center and spread</title>
      <link>/blog/la-center-spread/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/la-center-spread/</guid>
      <description>Center-and-spread Little App: Household income (as a multiplier of the poverty level) versus whether the household owns or rents their home. Note the skew distribution for renters. Click here to launch.   
The Center-and-spread Little App displays a jittered point plot of the response variable, which can be annotated with a variety of statistics often used to quantify “center” and “spread.”
 Standard deviation “ruler” helps clarify that the sd is a distance rather than a value of the variable.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Variation and the 95% summary interval</title>
      <link>/blog/activity-summary-interval/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/activity-summary-interval/</guid>
      <description>Get formatted versions: Word : PDF
Orientation Why is the word variable used to describe a column of a data frame? In mathematics, a variable is an unknown quantity. In math class, when they say “solve for x,” they mean figure out what the value of unknown x is.
In statistics, a variable is different. It’s a known quantity – known because you measured it, known because there it is, right in the data frame.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Experiment and causality</title>
      <link>/blog/activity-experiment-and-causality/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/activity-experiment-and-causality/</guid>
      <description>Get formatted versions: Word : PDF
Orientation Consider a situation where you have three variables: X, Y, and C. Your understanding of how the world works is telling you that X causes Y. And, indeed, when you collect data, you see an association between X and Y. But all an association does is to tell you that X and Y are connected somehow, not what that connection is.
If you’re trying to convince a skeptic that X causes Y, you have some work to do.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The standard deviation and the 95% summary interval</title>
      <link>/blog/activity-sd-and-summary-interval/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/activity-sd-and-summary-interval/</guid>
      <description>Get formatted versions: Word : PDF
Orientation The length of the 95% summary interval is a pretty good way to describe the amount of variation in a variable. Yet statisticians tend to prefer using the standard deviation. This makes sense, since statisticians are interested in confusing the poor student by using obscure names (“Deviation?”. Really?) and formulas that can be hard to understand. … Not really!! Even though the standard deviation has an odd name and seems complicated, the actual reason it’s used so much by statisticians is that it has some nice mathematical properties.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Two-sample t-test</title>
      <link>/blog/activity-two-sample-t/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/activity-two-sample-t/</guid>
      <description>T-test Little App: Weight versus self-described level of activity in the National Health and Nutrition Evaluation Survey. Click here to launch.   
The t-test Little App connects the t-interval to the .
 Length of confidence intervals as a function of n. Examine variation in the means and intervals by taking new samples from the population. Use the measuring stick to look at differences in means, lengths of confidence intervals, overlaps between confidence intervals, etc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Intervention and prediction</title>
      <link>/blog/activity-intervention-and-prediction/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/activity-intervention-and-prediction/</guid>
      <description>Get formatted versions: Word : PDF
Orientation The appropriate choice of one variable as the response and other variables as the explanatory depends on the purpose for which you want to describe the relationship.
Consider these two distinct purposes:
“I plan to intervene to change the value of variable B, and I want to know how A will change in response.” (Example: “I’m going to turn down the thermostat setting, and I want to know whether water will condense on my windows.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Common, uncommon, and rare</title>
      <link>/blog/activity-common-and-rare/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/activity-common-and-rare/</guid>
      <description>Get formatted versions: Word : PDF
Orientation English has many words to describe what statistician’s call frequency: common, unusual, rare, infrequent, uncommon, and so on. There’s no precise, numerical meaning to these words; they are used to create an impression.
In statistics, it’s helpful to have standard ways to refer to frequency. The standard deviation provides a widely accepted measure of commonality or rareness. It’s not just statisticians who use this measure.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Linear regression</title>
      <link>/blog/la-linear-regression/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/la-linear-regression/</guid>
      <description>Regression Little App: Systolic versus diastolic blood pressure from the National Health and Nutrition Evaluation Survey. Click here to launch.   
The linear regression Little App displays a jittered point plot of two quantitative variables. Upon this is layered two annotations:
A regression model. By default this is simple linear regression, but you can also incorporate a covariate and add curvature to the model. Two sets of short horizontal bars to the right of the graph, together with an interval showing the standard deviation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introducing linear regression</title>
      <link>/blog/activity-introducing-linear-regression/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/activity-introducing-linear-regression/</guid>
      <description>Get formatted versions: Word : PDF
Showing various sorts of relationships for discussion Open up the linear regression Little App. (See footnote1). In this activity we’ll explore three different data sets available through the app. For each data set, the variable indicated below plays the role of the response variable. Some explanatory variables are listed as sub-points.
Data set: NHANES. Response variable: BMI. It’s important for students to know what BMI is.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shapes of distributions</title>
      <link>/blog/activity-distribution-shapes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/activity-distribution-shapes/</guid>
      <description>Get formatted versions: Word : PDF
Orientation As you’ve probably figured out already, the columns of data frames are called variables because the values in the column are not all the same, that is, they vary.
In the early 1800s, it was discovered that many different variables have a pattern in common: the most common values are near the mean and values become less common the further they are from the mean.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Guidelines from GAISE/ASA/AMATYC</title>
      <link>/blog/presentation-gaise-asa/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/presentation-gaise-asa/</guid>
      <description>The Guidelines for Assessment and Instruction in Statistics Education The GAISE report (2016) was produced by a committee of leading statistical educators and endorsed by the ASA and AMATYC. It gives specific recommendations and some examples about best practices in teaching statistics.
Goals for intro stats  Goal 1. Students should become critical consumers of statistically-based results reported in popular media, recognizing whether reported results reasonably follow from the study and analysis conducted.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Parameters of the normal distribution</title>
      <link>/blog/activity-normal-parameters/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/activity-normal-parameters/</guid>
      <description>Get formatted versions: Word : PDF
Orientation The bell-shaped distribution is often a good description of the distribution of a variable, so often that it’s called the “normal” distribution.
Actually, there is not just one normal distribution but a whole family of them, all of which have the characteristic bell shape. To identify an individual member of this bell family, two numbers suffice:
 the mean: the location of the peak of the bell the standard deviation: the width of the bell  What’s potentially confusing here is that you may know about the mean in terms of a calculation you do on a variable: add up the n values and divide by n.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Instructor Guide: Causality</title>
      <link>/blog/instructions-causality/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/instructions-causality/</guid>
      <description>Activities  Intervention and prediction Experiment and causality   Learning objectives  Additional sections  Get formatted versions: Word : PDF Instructor orientation Role in statistical practice Classroom discussion Tips for an active classroom Student pre-requisites Pitfalls   Orientation for instructors There is an epigram that is familiar to all statistics instructors:
 Correlation is not causation.
 Put on a more explicit logical footing, this is equivalent to:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>R Tutorials for instructors</title>
      <link>/blog/tutorials/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/tutorials/</guid>
      <description>StatPREP tutorials A StatPREP tutorial is an interactive document mainly intended to help instructors develop statistical, graphical, and general computing skills using R statements.
This page provides links to instructor tutorials. Each link takes you to a web service that displays the document in your web browser. You don’t need to install any other software on your computer to use the lessons and tutorials.
If you’re looking for materials for use in class or other student-oriented settings, follow these links to StatPREP activites or Little Apps</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is a confidence interval?</title>
      <link>/blog/activity-what-is-a-confidence-interval/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/activity-what-is-a-confidence-interval/</guid>
      <description>Get formatted versions: Word : PDF
Orientation Statistics includes many forms and procedures for expressing uncertainty. A simple one is the assignment of a probability to a potential outcome. For instance, if we say the chance of rain tomorrow is 50%, we are expressing a large amount of uncertainty. In contrast, if the probability is specified as 10%, we are expressing much more certainty.
Another setting in which it’s helpful to express uncertainty involves a sample statistic such as the mean, standard deviation, median, correlation, regression slope, etc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sampling bias and the confidence interval</title>
      <link>/blog/activity-sampling-bias/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/activity-sampling-bias/</guid>
      <description>Get formatted versions: Word : PDF
Orientation The lesson on What is a confidence interval? showed how confidence intervals are supposed to behave. Specifically, a 95% confidence interval should cover the corresponding population parameter for 95% of possible samples. Achieving this performance of course depends on the confidence interval being calculated with an appropriate procedure. But it also depends on the sample being unbiased.
An unbiased sample is one where each member of the population has exactly the same probability of being included in a sample.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tidy Data</title>
      <link>/blog/presentation-tidy-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/presentation-tidy-data/</guid>
      <description>td,th { padding: 5px; }  GAISE 2016 Teach statistical thinking.  Teach statistics as an investigative process of problem-solving and decision-making. Give students experience with multivariable thinking.  Focus on conceptual understanding.
 Integrate real data with a context and purpose.
 Foster active learning.
 Use technology to explore concepts and analyze data.
 Use assessments to improve and evaluate student learning.
   Real data The StatPREP definition:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Articulation &amp; Transfer</title>
      <link>/blog/articulation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/articulation/</guid>
      <description>Florida STA2023 Statistical Methods I General Education Core TOPICS: 1. PROBABILITY 2. RANDOM VARIABLES. 3. HYPOTHESIS TESTING. 4. CONFIDENCE INTERVAL ESTIMATION 5. SMALL SAMPLE METHODS. 6. CORRELATION. 7. SIMPLE LINEAR REGRESSION. 8. NONPARAMETRIC STATISTICS
The STA2023 course is taught at all public Florida institutions. The STA2023 course is the only gen ed statistics course taught at the Florida State Colleges (Florida State Colleges are primarily two-year colleges). The STA2023 course is the first course taken for the statistics major or concentration at the Florida Universities (four year schools).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sources of curated data  for teaching stats</title>
      <link>/blog/data-curated-data-sources/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/data-curated-data-sources/</guid>
      <description>Statistical Science Web Journal of Statistical Education data archive. These data sets were collected for the purpose of teaching statistics. One advantage of them is that there is often a JSE article associated with the data which gives context and a statistically informed discussion. Here are a very few …  Body shape measurements African conflict data Gardacil vaccine study NASCAR Profiles from OK Cupid. This is the GitHub repo which contains the PDF of the article, as well as the codebook and dataset.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Comparing two groups</title>
      <link>/blog/activity-comparing-two-groups/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/activity-comparing-two-groups/</guid>
      <description>Get formatted versions: Word : PDF
Orientation A friend and I were discussing ways to measure poverty. Of course, there’s the so-called “poverty level” of income defined by the US government. But we were interested in whether it might be worthwhile to do a detailed interview with, say, 100 families, quantifying how much trouble they have paying for different things: food, housing, healthcare, transportation, emergencies, etc. Then we’d look at easy things to measure so that we could have an index for these different things, food stress, housing stress, and so on.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Instructor guide: Center &amp; spread</title>
      <link>/blog/instructions-center-spread/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/instructions-center-spread/</guid>
      <description>Activities  Variables and their summary intervals The standard deviation and the summary interval Shapes of distributions The normal distribution   Learning objectives Summarize the likely range of a variable using an interval. Choose the summary interval endpoints to include the “vast majority” of the values. Master the convention that “vast majority” is the central 95% of the values. Be able to work with two formats for describing an interval: “A to B” and “C ± D”.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Grammatical graphics</title>
      <link>/blog/presentation-grammatical-graphics/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Jun 2017 13:07:31 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/presentation-grammatical-graphics/</guid>
      <description>The Grammar of Graphics The title comes from Leland Wilkinson’s book, The Grammar of Graphics
The first chapter is quite mathematical – give it a look by following the link above.
One purpose was to give a way of describing graphics in the face of a combinatorial explosion of designs.
 How to describe graphics to the computer for drawing.  But it also provides a way for teaching graphics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DATA SOURCE:  Locke5 Datasets</title>
      <link>/blog/data-lock5data/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/data-lock5data/</guid>
      <description>The textbook Statistics: Unlocking the Power of Data (2/e 2017) by Lock, Lock, Lock, Lock, and Lock has publicly available datasets and interactive applets.
A list of the more than 100 datasets in the collection is available at this site. There is also an R package, Lock5Data, that contains documentation for the data.
Example: Restaurant tips The data frame RestaurantTips contains, … well let’s look directly at the documentation.
library(Lock5Data) help(RestaurantTips) ## _R_e_s_t_a_u_r_a_n_t _T_i_p_s ## ## _D_e_s_c_r_i_p_t_i_o_n: ## ## Tip data from the First Crush Bistro ## ## _F_o_r_m_a_t: ## ## A dataset with 157 observations on the following 7 variables.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DATA SOURCE: FiveThirtyEight Blog</title>
      <link>/blog/data-fivethirtyeight/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/data-fivethirtyeight/</guid>
      <description>The FiveThirtyEight news organization publishes on a daily basis investigations based on data. The organization is perhaps best known for it’s consolidation of political polling results, but there are many, many other investigation topics as well.
One way to scan relatively quickly through the available data is via their GitHub site. Don’t be put off by the techie-sounding name. Direct your browser to this address.
The page looks like this:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Comparing two confidence intervals</title>
      <link>/blog/activity-comparing-confidence-intervals/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/activity-comparing-confidence-intervals/</guid>
      <description>Get formatted versions: Word : PDF
Orientation We’re continuing the story of two friends interested in how to measure poverty. You met with them at a coffee shop to show them the NHANES data and how to display it in the t-test Little App. You had arranged the display to have income_poverty as the response variable and home_type as the explanatory variable. The sample size was n = 100, since that’s the number of families your friends were thinking of interviewing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The two-sample t test</title>
      <link>/blog/activity-two-sample-t-test/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/activity-two-sample-t-test/</guid>
      <description>Get formatted versions: Word : PDF
Orientation Suppose you have an explanatory variable that defines two, distinct groups, like the home_type variable in the NHANES2 data. You notice that the two groups have different mean values for the explanatory variable.
A possible explanation for the observed difference in the two means is that it is just a pattern that reflects the play of chance rather than any systematic difference in the population of the two groups,</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>From Github to Sesame Street</title>
      <link>/blog/data-sesame/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/data-sesame/</guid>
      <description>NOTE: This information is taken from Prof. Jerry Reiter’s website for his Stat 210 course at Duke University.
The television series Sesame Street is concerned mainly with teaching preschool skills to children age 3-5, with special emphasis on reaching economically disadvantaged children. The show is designed to hold young childrens’ attention through action oriented, short duration presentations teaching specific preschool cognitive skills and some social skills. Each show is one hour and involves much repetition of concepts within and across shows.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DATA SOURCE: Hospital infections</title>
      <link>/blog/data-infections/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/data-infections/</guid>
      <description>Medicare data &amp;lt;data.medicare.gov/Hospital-Compare&amp;gt;: A web site suggested by Kim Druschel at Saint Louis University
One dataset there is about infections associated with hospitalization. https://data.medicare.gov/Hospital-Compare/Healthcare-Associated-Infections-Hospital/77hc-ibv8
Download as CSV In RStudio, go to Environment/ImportDataset   Wrangling data: library(dplyr, quietly = TRUE, verbose = FALSE) library(readr, quietly = TRUE, verbose = FALSE) Infections &amp;lt;- readr::read_csv(&amp;quot;~/Downloads/Healthcare_Associated_Infections_-_Hospital.csv&amp;quot;) ## Parsed with column specification: ## cols( ## `Provider ID` = col_character(), ## `Hospital Name` = col_character(), ## Address = col_character(), ## City = col_character(), ## State = col_character(), ## `ZIP Code` = col_double(), ## `County Name` = col_character(), ## `Phone Number` = col_double(), ## `Measure Name` = col_character(), ## `Measure ID` = col_character(), ## `Compared to National` = col_character(), ## Score = col_character(), ## Footnote = col_character(), ## `Measure Start Date` = col_character(), ## `Measure End Date` = col_character(), ## Location = col_character() ## ) unique(Infections$`Measure Name`) ## [1] &amp;quot;MRSA Bacteremia&amp;quot; ## [2] &amp;quot;Clostridium Difficile (C.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DATA SOURCE: Big data from machine-learning sites</title>
      <link>/blog/data-machine-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/data-machine-learning/</guid>
      <description>One source of fairly large datasets is machine-learning repositories or contests such as Kaggle.
This example concerns a dataset available at a repository from the University of California at Irvine.
The data set, available here, is about YouTube viewer’s preferences among comedy videos. Attractive features of the dataset are:
It has a simple structure: just three variables. The videos are (often?) still available on YouTube, providing some motivation for working with the data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DATA SOURCE: Case study on Soil Moisture</title>
      <link>/blog/data-awesome-soil/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/data-awesome-soil/</guid>
      <description>The website Awesome public datasets contains links to several hundred datasets. This example deals with a randomly selected one, Hyperspectral benchmark dataset on soil moisture
That dataset is described as being a sequence of measurements of a soil sample, recording temperature, soil moisture, and the intensity at each of 125 light frequency bands (in nm) of an image of the sample.
Process Download the ZIP file. Uncompress the ZIP file  This results in a directory with a CSV file, a README.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Instructor Guide: Confidence intervals</title>
      <link>/blog/instructions-confidence-intervals/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/instructions-confidence-intervals/</guid>
      <description>Activities  What is a confidence interval? Sampling bias and confidence intervals Comparing two groups Comparing two confidence intervals Two-sample t test   Learning objectives connected to confidence intervals  Master the relevant vocabulary … population, sample, sample statistic, point estimate, margin of error, confidence interval, confidence level. Recognize the estimation process that leads to a confidence interval: a sample is selected randomly from a population a statistic is calculated from that sample the margin of error and, correspondingly, the confidence interval are calculated from that sample.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Describing relationship patterns in words and numbers</title>
      <link>/blog/activity-relationship-patterns/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/activity-relationship-patterns/</guid>
      <description>Get formatted versions: Word : PDF
Orientation It’s natural to display a linear regression as a graph modeling the response variable as a function of the explanatory variables. In the LA_linear_regression Little App, that function is shown as a line laid on top of the data.
Graphics are important, but it’s also a good practice to summarize the relationship using words and numbers.
This lesson introduces the conventions for such a summary.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How much is explained?</title>
      <link>/blog/activity-how-much-is-explained/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/activity-how-much-is-explained/</guid>
      <description>Get formatted versions: Word : PDF
Orientation The statistical work we do is built around models. If the word “model” reminds you of a toy plane, you’re on the right track. A model is something we build in order to represent something in the real world. Usually the model is much simpler than the real-world object.
Models are useful when they serve a purpose. For instance, a toy plane can serve the purpose of teaching a child what are the main components of a plane and how they are related.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>It&#39;s all regression</title>
      <link>/blog/presentation-its-all-regression/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/presentation-its-all-regression/</guid>
      <description>We almost always work with variables that are either …
 quantitative categorical with only two levels  In relating two variables, there are four possible situations
      Quantitative Categorical         Quant. slope of regression line or correlation coefficient difference in two means  …………. …………………………………… ……………………………………….  Categ. ?????? difference in two proportions    Presentation in terms of algebra       Quantitative Categorical         Quant.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data and Point Plots</title>
      <link>/blog/activity-point-plot/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/activity-point-plot/</guid>
      <description>Get formatted versions: Word : PDF
Orientation Data can be many things, but one of the most common formats is a data frame, a kind of spreadsheet of rows and columns. We’ll work with the data frame Births_2014, which is based on data published by the US Centers for Disease Control. Births_2014 has 100,000 rows. Each row reports a live birth in the US in 2014. There are dozens of variables, a few of which are shown below.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flexibility</title>
      <link>/blog/activity-flexibility/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/activity-flexibility/</guid>
      <description>Get formatted versions: Word : PDF
Orientation  Activity Systolic versus diastolic in NHANES. A stiff line is too strongly influenced by the people with very low diastolic blood pressure. Adding some flexibility allows the relationship for those with normal pressure to be more evident. I’m guessing very low diastolic pressure is OK, but you can’t lower systolic pressure accordingly and stay alive.
Version 0.2, 2019-06-04, Daniel Kaplan, Word version</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Changes in risk</title>
      <link>/blog/activity-changes-in-risk/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/activity-changes-in-risk/</guid>
      <description>Get formatted versions: Word : PDF
Orientation  Activity proportions little app
Version 0.2, 2019-06-04, Daniel Kaplan, Word version
 </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Joining MAA Connect</title>
      <link>/blog/community-maa-connect/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/community-maa-connect/</guid>
      <description>We are excited to invite you to join the StatPREP Hub Communities online group using MAA Connect!
Below, you will find instructions on logging into MAA Connect if you are a MAA member, or registering for a guest account if you are not. You will also find general set-up instructions, as well as information on accessing the different communities you want to join. We encourage you to read/listen along to these instructions as you are getting logged in for the first time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stats for Data Science</title>
      <link>/blog/stats-for-data-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/stats-for-data-science/</guid>
      <description>Stats for Data Science is a forward-looking introductory-level textbook currently in draft form. The book is available on-line here.
From the preface … Data science is an emerging computational discipline with roots sprouting in contemporary problems. Almost always these problems involve large amounts of data collected by automated systems and collated by bringing together diverse data from different sources. The goals for working with such data are varied: predicting the preferences of individual people for consumer products or news feeds; examining government or business or clinical medical records to answer questions such as the efficacy of a proposed program or intervention in public health; detecting and classifying rare events such as credit-card fraud; finding useful patterns in clouds of text or data that might help identify harmful interactions between medicines or extract meaning from thousands of documents.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tutorials from Stats for Data Science</title>
      <link>/blog/tutorials-from-stats-for-data-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/tutorials-from-stats-for-data-science/</guid>
      <description>Stats for Data Science is a forward-looking introductory-level textbook currently in draft form. Each chapter has will have a short tutorial introducing the computing techniques relevant to that chapter. The tutorials from the initial chapters may be helpful to those starting out with R.
 Starting out with R Basics of the R language Functions and arguments Accessing data Data graphics  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>You Want to Know: Cases, Variables, and Study Goals</title>
      <link>/blog/activity-you-want-to-know/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/activity-you-want-to-know/</guid>
      <description>Instructions. In each scenario below,
 determine what variables you would need to collect and whether each is categorical or quantitative,
 describe or sketch a graph you would make to give you an initial impression regarding the answer to the question of interest,
 determine the parameter(s) of interest and explain how they are different from the variables,
   determine whether you are using a paired design.  Sometimes there may be more than one way to design the study, but don’t design a poor study when a better option is available.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>You Want to Know: What&#39;s the Point?</title>
      <link>/blog/instructions-you-want-to-know/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/instructions-you-want-to-know/</guid>
      <description>The You Want to Know activity is just one example among many similar activities. This instructors’ activity explores ways you can construct many similar activities for your students.
How to make your own activity The key steps to creating these activities are
Determine the learning objectives. These might include
Making key distinctions like case/variable, categorical/quantitative, explantory/reponse, etc. Identifying key elements of study design. Selecting appropriate analysis methods. Use of software to acheive a task (have students write R command or describe how to use other software)  Design the questions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data sources</title>
      <link>/blog/presentation-data-sources/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/presentation-data-sources/</guid>
      <description>More documents at the data-sources directory
Real data At the October 2018 StatPREP meeting at the Mathematical Association of America’s DC headquarters the new MAA deputy executive director, Rachel Levy asked a simple question: What’s real data?
A core recommendation of the American Statistical Association’s GAISE report is to “use real data” when teaching statistics. Prof. Levy wasn’t looking to prompt a philosophical discussion of the nature of reality, but to define a benchmark.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>FAIL!</title>
      <link>/blog/fail/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/fail/</guid>
      <description>th,hd { padding: 5px; }  These are textbook examples of the presentation of data in ways that encourage bad habits.
No columns This might look like a data frame, but the individual columns have no meaning and the rows are not a unit of observation.
Should be:
  person time sex    id792 4.3 F  id796 4.3 F  id797 4.5 M    … and so on.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Instructor Guide: Two-sample t-test</title>
      <link>/blog/instructions-two-sample-t-test/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/instructions-two-sample-t-test/</guid>
      <description>Activities  Comparing two groups Comparing confidence intervals Two sample t-test Instructor customizations:  Ambika Silva: Comparing two samples with confidence intervals activity &amp;amp; assessment    Learning objectives Typical course objectives relating to the t-based test and confidence interval are:
 Confidence interval:  Compute from data the confidence interval on the difference of means. Interpret the confidence interval in the context of the question intended to be addressed with the data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Instructor Guide: Introducing the normal distribution</title>
      <link>/blog/instructions-normal-distribution/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/instructions-normal-distribution/</guid>
      <description>Activities  Distribution shapes Normal parameters Common and rare   Learning objectives  Understand how a distribution summarizes the properties of a collection of individual values. Be able to translate between major forms of representing distributions graphically, e.g.  the density of points in a (jittered) point plot the presentation of such density as a height or width as in a violin or density plot  Be able to eyeball the standard deviation of a close-to-normal distribution and, similarly, a 95% summary interval (that is, mean ± two standard deviations ) Be able to identify common characteristics of skew or long-tailed distributions, by comparison to a normal distribution.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Instructor Guide: Linear Regression</title>
      <link>/blog/instructions-linear-regression/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/instructions-linear-regression/</guid>
      <description>Activities  Introducing linear regression Describing relationship patterns How much is explained by regression?   Learning objectives connected to linear regression  Create scatterplots for bivariate data using graphing technology where appropriate. Lesson: point plots Sensibly choose which variable should be the response and which the explanatory variable, and know when it does and doesn’t matter. (Other nomenclature for explanatory/response: predictor/response or independent/dependent.) Lesson: response and explanatory variables  External evidence of which direction causation goes, e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contact</title>
      <link>/contact/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/contact/</guid>
      <description>We are here to help you Are you curious about something? Do you have some kind of problem with our products? As am hastily invited settled at limited civilly fortune me. Really spring in extent an by. Judge but built gay party world. Of so am he remember although required. Bachelor unpacked be advanced at. Confined in declared marianne is vicinity.
Please feel free to contact us, our customer service center is working for you 24&amp;frasl;7.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>FAQ</title>
      <link>/faq/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/faq/</guid>
      <description>Pellentesque habitant morbi tristique senectus et netus et malesuada fames ac turpis egestas. Vestibulum tortor quam, feugiat vitae, ultricies eget, tempor sit amet, ante. Donec eu libero sit amet quam egestas semper. Aenean ultricies mi vitae est. Mauris placerat eleifend leo.
1. WHAT TO DO IF I HAVE STILL NOT RECEIVED THE ORDER? Pellentesque habitant morbi tristique senectus et netus et malesuada fames ac turpis egestas. Vestibulum tortor quam, feugiat vitae, ultricies eget, tempor sit amet, ante.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tips for an active classroom</title>
      <link>/blog/tips-for-active-classroom/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/tips-for-active-classroom/</guid>
      <description>Many instructors believe that learning is enhanced in a classroom where students are active participants rather than the passive recipients of a lecture. This document describes some general techniques for fostering an active classroom that can be used in a wide range of lesson topics. (There are also tips for specific topics included in the instructor guide for each topic.)
What’s key is to constantly look for opportunities to force students to make a choice, offer a suggestion, or state an interpretation or an opinion.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Workshop schedule: Hartford</title>
      <link>/blog/schedule-hartford/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/schedule-hartford/</guid>
      <description>Before the Workshop  Answer these questions (on paper) and bring to the workshop.   Friday May 31, 2019  1:30 pm: Registration 2:00 pm: Welcome &amp;amp; housekeeping Announcements 2:15 pm: Icebreaker: Teaching Statistics 2:30 pm: GAISE and ASA/AMATYC guidelines to teaching statistics 2:50 pm: Tidy data &amp;amp; grammatical graphics 3:20 pm: Break 3:30 pm: Orientation to the StatPREP website and Little Apps: Kate Kozak 4:00 pm: Using StatPREP Little Apps in the Classroom Activity #1: Center and spread with Kate Kozak 4:50 pm: Break 5:00 pm: Introduction to RStudio cloud 6:00 pm: Dinner-time discussion of statewide curriculum 6:45 pm: Share out / Adjourn Day 1   Saturday June 1, 2019  8:00 am: Breakfast 8:30 am: Tutorials with R 9:00 am: Using StatPREP Little Apps in the Classroom Activity #2: Normal distribution with Kate Kozak 9:45 am: Searching for Data: Finding good sources of data 10:20 am: Break 10:30 am: Using StatPREP Little Apps in the Classroom Activity #3: Confidence intervals with Ambika Silva 11:15 am: Bootstrapping with the Little App, with Danny and Nick 11:45 am: Using StatPREP Little Apps in the Classroom Activity #4: Two-sample t-test with Danny and Nick 12:30 pm: Lunchtime Discussion: continuation of yesterday’s discussion on curriculum and state standards 1:15 pm: Choose one of the following to attend:  Workout with a personal trainer: your choice Little Apps/Tutorials/basics of R/…  The OSHA.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Workshop schedule: Howard Community College</title>
      <link>/schedule/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/schedule/</guid>
      <description>Before the Workshop  Answer these questions (on paper) and bring to the workshop.   Friday June 7, 2019  1:30 pm - 2:00 pm: Registration 2:00 pm - 2:15 pm: Welcome &amp;amp; housekeeping Announcements 2:15 pm - 2:30 pm: Icebreaker: Teaching Statistics 2:30 pm - 2:50 pm: GAISE and ASA/AMATYC guidelines to teaching statistics (Andy Zieffler) 2:50 pm - 3:20 pm: Tidy data (Randy Pruim)
 3:20 pm - 3:30 pm: Break</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>