<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Little App on StatPREP Workshops 2019</title>
    <link>/categories/little-app/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Little App on StatPREP Workshops 2019</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 16 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/little-app/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
<<<<<<< HEAD
      <title>Little Apps: Orientation</title>
      <link>/blog/la-orientation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/la-orientation/</guid>
      <description>Little Apps provide interactive computing with no coding to calculate statistics, fit models, and display statistical concepts.
Every Little App is built around a common framework:
 At the core is a data graphic. The vertical axis is the response variable and the horizontal axis is the explanatory variable. Controls enable you to select a data set and variables. Set the sample size and easily display a new sample. Statistics are shown as annotations, always with respect to the data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bootstrapping</title>
      <link>/blog/la-bootstrap/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/la-bootstrap/</guid>
      <description>Bootstrapping Little App: Baby weight versus gestation in Births_2014. Click here to launch.   
The bootstrapping little app is a little different than most of the others: it’s graphic illustrates a concept rather than providing a means to explore data.
The concept, of course, is the confidence interval. Rather than using a formula to compute the standard error, in bootstrapping you draw a new sample from the sample itself in order to indicate the amount of sampling variability.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
=======
>>>>>>> 47a4a15c39d5910e08ec415669a57f18c7bc9f09
      <title>Introduction to data graphics</title>
      <link>/blog/la-point-plot/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/la-point-plot/</guid>
      <description>Point plot Little App: Baby weight versus gestation in Births_2014. Click here to launch.   
The point-plot Little App provides a quick path to making data graphics. Select the data set, the response and explanatory variables, and you’re there.
 You can map color to a covariate and can facet the graph (as shown above) by another covariate. Works with both quantitative and categorical variables on either or both axes, for color, and for faceting.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Little Apps: Orientation</title>
      <link>/blog/la-orientation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/la-orientation/</guid>
      <description>Little Apps provide interactive computing with no coding to calculate statistics, fit models, and display statistical concepts.
Every Little App is built around a common framework:
 At the core is a data graphic. The vertical axis is the response variable and the horizontal axis is the explanatory variable. Controls enable you to select a data set and variables. Set the sample size and easily display a new sample. Statistics are shown as annotations, always with respect to the data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Jittering</title>
      <link>/blog/la-jittering/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/la-jittering/</guid>
      <description>  Jittering Little App: Self-described level of health versus frequency of feeling depressed in the National Health and Nutrition Evaluation Survey. Click here to launch.   
The Jittering Little App shows how the general point-plot can be effective even when variables are categorical.
 Students can adjust the amount of jittering and transparency. Can stratify sampling by the explanatory variable.  Suggested StatPREP 101 activities  Jittering activity   </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Proportions</title>
      <link>/blog/la-proportions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/la-proportions/</guid>
      <description>Proportions Little App: Among births in the US, does the probability of an induced delivery vary with the length of gestation? Click here to launch.   
The Proportions Little App allows you to explore how the probability of a categorical outcome varies with either categorical or quantitative variables.
 Choose the level of the response variable for which you want to know the proportion. Display confidence intervals/bands.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Center and spread</title>
      <link>/blog/la-center-spread/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/la-center-spread/</guid>
      <description>Center-and-spread Little App: Household income (as a multiplier of the poverty level) versus whether the household owns or rents their home. Note the skew distribution for renters. Click here to launch.   
The Center-and-spread Little App displays a jittered point plot of the response variable, which can be annotated with a variety of statistics often used to quantify “center” and “spread.”
 Standard deviation “ruler” helps clarify that the sd is a distance rather than a value of the variable.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Two-sample t-test</title>
      <link>/blog/activity-two-sample-t/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/activity-two-sample-t/</guid>
      <description>T-test Little App: Weight versus self-described level of activity in the National Health and Nutrition Evaluation Survey. Click here to launch.   
The t-test Little App connects the t-interval to the .
 Length of confidence intervals as a function of n. Examine variation in the means and intervals by taking new samples from the population. Use the measuring stick to look at differences in means, lengths of confidence intervals, overlaps between confidence intervals, etc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Linear regression</title>
      <link>/blog/la-linear-regression/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/la-linear-regression/</guid>
      <description>Regression Little App: Systolic versus diastolic blood pressure from the National Health and Nutrition Evaluation Survey. Click here to launch.   
The linear regression Little App displays a jittered point plot of two quantitative variables. Upon this is layered two annotations:
A regression model. By default this is simple linear regression, but you can also incorporate a covariate and add curvature to the model. Two sets of short horizontal bars to the right of the graph, together with an interval showing the standard deviation.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>