<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Confidence Interval on StatPREP Workshops 2019</title>
    <link>/tags/confidence-interval/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Confidence Interval on StatPREP Workshops 2019</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 05 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/confidence-interval/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>What is a confidence interval?</title>
      <link>/blog/activity-what-is-a-confidence-interval/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/activity-what-is-a-confidence-interval/</guid>
      <description>Get formatted versions: Word : PDF
Orientation Statistics includes many forms and procedures for expressing uncertainty. A simple one is the assignment of a probability to a potential outcome. For instance, if we say the chance of rain tomorrow is 50%, we are expressing a large amount of uncertainty. In contrast, if the probability is specified as 10%, we are expressing much more certainty.
Another setting in which it’s helpful to express uncertainty involves a sample statistic such as the mean, standard deviation, median, correlation, regression slope, etc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Comparing two groups</title>
      <link>/blog/activity-comparing-two-groups/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/activity-comparing-two-groups/</guid>
      <description>Get formatted versions: Word : PDF
Orientation A friend and I were discussing ways to measure poverty. Of course, there’s the so-called “poverty level” of income defined by the US government. But we were interested in whether it might be worthwhile to do a detailed interview with, say, 100 families, quantifying how much trouble they have paying for different things: food, housing, healthcare, transportation, emergencies, etc. Then we’d look at easy things to measure so that we could have an index for these different things, food stress, housing stress, and so on.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Instructor Guide: Confidence intervals</title>
      <link>/blog/instructions-confidence-intervals/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/instructions-confidence-intervals/</guid>
      <description>Activities  What is a confidence interval? Sampling bias and confidence intervals Comparing two groups Comparing two confidence intervals Two-sample t test   Learning objectives connected to confidence intervals  Master the relevant vocabulary … population, sample, sample statistic, point estimate, margin of error, confidence interval, confidence level. Recognize the estimation process that leads to a confidence interval: a sample is selected randomly from a population a statistic is calculated from that sample the margin of error and, correspondingly, the confidence interval are calculated from that sample.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>