<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Tidy Data on StatPREP Workshops 2019</title>
    <link>/tags/tidy-data/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Tidy Data on StatPREP Workshops 2019</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/tidy-data/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Instructor Guide: Data basics</title>
      <link>/blog/instructions-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/instructions-data/</guid>
      <description>Activities  Variable types Variables and units Response and explanatory variables   Learning objectives  Additional resources  Get formatted versions: Word : PDF Instructor orientation Role in statistical practice Classroom discussion Assessment Tips for an active classroom Student pre-requisites Pitfalls   Orientation for instructors Explaining what is data and what are the forms of data.
Role in statistical practice  Conceptual pitfalls  Student pre-requisites  Student tasks and activities  Creating an active classroom See the document on general tips for creating an active classroom.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>You Want to Know: Cases, Variables, and Study Goals</title>
      <link>/blog/activity-you-want-to-know/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/activity-you-want-to-know/</guid>
      <description>Instructions. In each scenario below,
 determine what variables you would need to collect and whether each is categorical or quantitative,
 describe or sketch a graph you would make to give you an initial impression regarding the answer to the question of interest,
 determine the parameter(s) of interest and explain how they are different from the variables,
   determine whether you are using a paired design.  Sometimes there may be more than one way to design the study, but don’t design a poor study when a better option is available.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>You Want to Know: What&#39;s the Point?</title>
      <link>/blog/instructions-you-want-to-know/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/instructions-you-want-to-know/</guid>
      <description>The You Want to Know activity is just one example among many similar activities. This instructors’ activity explores ways you can construct many similar activities for your students.
How to make your own activity The key steps to creating these activities are
Determine the learning objectives. These might include
Making key distinctions like case/variable, categorical/quantitative, explantory/reponse, etc. Identifying key elements of study design. Selecting appropriate analysis methods. Use of software to acheive a task (have students write R command or describe how to use other software)  Design the questions.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>